Alamance County CR.001
State Archives of North Carolina
Alamance County
CR.001
201
Alamance County (N.C.)
Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
State Archives of North Carolina
Clerk of Superior Court, Register of Deeds
Scope and Content
Alamance County was established in 1849 from Orange County. No extensive losses of records are known.
Alamance County (N.C.)
- Bonds, Licenses, Oaths, and Registrations, CR.001.1; Alamance County (N.C.)
  Scope and Content
  This series may include Apprentice Bonds, Bastardy Bonds, Official Bonds and Records of county officials, Oaths taken by county officials, and other miscellaneous bonds and records pertaining to legal responsibilities of service granted through the courts, as well as Assumed Business Names, Corporations, and Partnerships and Brands or Marks registered in the county and Licenses and Registrations of merchants and professionals kept by the county.
  - Apprentice Bonds, 1878-1918; CR.001.101; 201.1.1; CR.001.101.1; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Apprentice Bonds)
    Transferred According to Retention Schedule
    Arrangement
    Chronological
    Records include contracts of apprenticeship, both formal and informal, which can include name of master and apprentice, trade to be taught, details of contract, amount of master's bond, and name of sureties. Other papers may include petitions for apprenticeship, petitions for "freedom dues" upon the completion of an apprenticeship, and civil and criminal actions concerning masters or wards.
  - Bastardy Bonds and Records, 1877-1917; CR.001.102; 1977.08.08; 201.2.1; CR.001.102.1; Alamance County (N.C.) (Box Bastardy Bonds and Records)
    Clerk of Superior Court
    Records include bonds posted by putative fathers of illegitimate children to insure the county against the children becoming public charges. Often give name of father and his bondsman, as well as that of the mother and child and the amount of the bond posted. Other papers may include presentments against and examinations of unwed mothers and mothers-to-be, warrants to bring the putative fathers to court, and receipts for payments made on behalf of bastard children.
- Court Records, CR.001.3; Alamance County (N.C.)
  Biographical/Historical
  County Courts of Pleas and Quarter Sessions evolved from precinct courts in 1738. The courts were composed of three or more Justices of the Peace and sat four times each year. The functions of county courts may be categorized into three distinct areas-judicial, probate and administrative-that are reflected in the minute dockets. The courts exercised both civil and criminal jurisdiction, original and appellate (from magistrates courts). Probate responsibilities included acknowledgment and probate of deeds; probate of wills; appointment and qualification of administrators, executors and guardians; binding of apprentices; and inquisitions of lunacy. The court also served as the governing body of the county, responsible for the appointment and qualification of local officials, levying of local taxes, expenditure of public funds, granting of licenses (tavern keepers, ferry operators, and peddlers), registration of stock marks, paternity inquisitions, and emancipation and manumission of slaves.
  Courts of Pleas and Quarter Sessions were abolished by the Constitution of 1868. The judicial functions devolved to county Superior Courts and Justices of the Peace Courts; the probate function was vested in the clerk of Superior Court; and administrative responsibilities were inherited by the newly created Boards of County Commissioners. Superior Courts were established in each county in 1806, replacing the district superior courts that had functioned since 1778. Originally, the county Superior Court sat twice each year, spring and fall terms, with six judges riding circuit. Each county had separate clerks for Law and for Equity. These courts had original and appellate civil and criminal jurisdiction, as well as jurisdiction over actions in equity. Criminal jurisdiction extended to serious felonies, such as murder, rape, larceny, house breaking, assault and battery, riot, and forgery; civil jurisdiction extended to suits involving $100 or more (after 1868, $200 or more). Other matters assigned to Superior Court included legitimization of bastards, emancipation and manumission of slaves, registration of aliens, and hearing of grand jury presentments and reports. Later, matters handled before a clerk were classified in Special Proceedings and Orders and Decrees, which included things such as adoptions, name changes, incompetency hearings, and many estate and guardian matters.
  This series includes records pertaining to the administration and actions of the county court system, particularly Civil and Criminal Actions before a jury and other actions before the court or the clerk, such as Special Proceedings. The dominant court prior to 1868 was known as the Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; after court reform circa 1868, it was known as the Superior Court.
  For court records concerning land and property matters, see also series 4, Land and Property Records. For records pertaining to Wills and Estate matters, see also series 5, Estates Records and Wills. For Adoptions, see also series 6, Marriage, Divorce and Vital Statistics. Series 10, subseries 928, may also contain loose court records.
  - Minute Dockets, Superior Court and Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1849-1968; CR.001.MD; Alamance County (N.C.)
    The minute dockets record the daily transactions of the court, generally recording judgments in civil and criminal actions or documenting non-juried matters. They also reflect the internal workings of the court, recording the appointment and qualification of clerks, the summoning and impaneling of juries, and the hearing of grand jury reports.
    - Minute Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1849-1868; CR.001.301; 201.6.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions.; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Minute Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions)
      County courts of pleas and quarter sessions evolved from precinct courts in 1738. The courts were composed of three or more justices of the peace and sat four times each year. The functions of county courts may be categorized into three distinct areas - judicial, probate and administrative - that are reflected in the minute dockets. The courts exercised both civil and criminal jurisdiction, original and appellate (from magistrates courts). Probate responsibilities included acknowledgment and probate of deeds, probate of wills, appointment and qualification of administrators, executors and guardians, binding of apprentices, and inquisitions of lunacy. The court also served as the governing body of the county, responsible for the appointment and qualification of local officials, levying of local taxes, expenditure of public funds, granting of licenses (tavern keepers, ferry operators, and peddlers), registration of stock marks, paternity inquisitions, and emancipation and manumission of slaves. Courts of pleas and quarter were abolished by the Constitution of 1868. The courts' judicial functions devolved to county superior courts and justices of the peace courts; the probate function was vested in the clerk of superior court; and administrative responsibilities were inherited by the newly created boards of county commissioners. This series my include both rough and smooth copies of the minutes.
    - Minute Docket, Superior Court, 1849-1968; CR.001.311; 201.16.1; 2014.10.36; CR.001.311.1 - CR.001.311.30; CR.001.311.31 [oversized]; CR.001.311.32 - CR.001.311.49; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Minute Docket, Superior Court)
    - Equity Minute Docket, Superior Court of Law and Equity, 1849-1872; CR.001.314; 1996.8.6; 201.19.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Alamance County (N.C.) (Item Equity Minute Docket, Superior Court of Law and Equity. Also contains clerk's receipt book (land sales), 1869-1872.)
      Minutes of the Superior Court of Law and Equity (1806-1868).
      Also contains clerk's receipt book (land sales), 1869-1872.
  - Judgment/Execution Dockets, Superior Court and Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1868-1968; CR.001.JE; Alamance County (N.C.)
    Equity Execution Dockets and Execution Dockets record the names of all parties involved in compensatory judgments awarded by the Court of Equity or Superior Court. Information includes names of parties to action; nature of action; amount of judgment; bill of costs; type of writ issued, its execution; satisfaction of judgment, in the case of Equity Execution Dockets; and sheriff's return. After 1868, in most counties this information was recorded in Judgment Dockets, although some continued to use separate Execution Dockets.
    - Cross Index to Judgments, 1899-1925; CR.001.324; 201.110.2; 2014.4.57; CR.001.324.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    - Judgment Docket, Superior Court, 1868-1968; CR.001.318; 201.110.1; 2014.4.55; CR.001.318.1 - CR.001.318.20; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      v.1-8; 8 1/2; 9 (part 1 and 2); 10-11; 13, 15, 17, 19, 21, 27-28
  - Criminal Dockets, Superior Court and Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1849-1868, 1941-1967; CR.001.CR; Alamance County (N.C.)
    Trials in criminal court were recorded in Crown Dockets in the colonial period, State Dockets from the colonial period to 1868, and Criminal Docket; Criminal Issues Docket; or Judgment Docket, State Cases, post-1868. [Recognizance Dockets track appearance in criminal court.]
    - Criminal Issues Docket, Superior Court, 1941-1967; CR.001.321; 201.107.1; 2014.4.50; CR.001.321.1 - CR.001.321.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Criminal docket tracking appearance and trial of state prosecutions. After 1868, known as Criminal Issues Docket.
      v.6 1941-1953; v7 1954-1967
    - State Docket, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1849-1868; CR.001.307; 1996.5.8; 201.12.1; 2016.4.72; CR.001.307.1 - CR.001.307.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Criminal docket tracking appearance and trial of state prosecutions. During the colonial period, known as Crown Docket.
  - Criminal Action Papers, Superior Court and Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1878-1968; CR.001.326; 1977.08.08; 201.31.1; 2015.8.3; CR.001.326.1 - CR.001.326.3; CR.001.326._; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Access Restriction
    Unprocessed county records require additional time to pull. Access to these records on Saturdays requires prior arrangements. Please consult the reference staff for more information.
    Criminal case files from magistrates courts, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, Superior Court, and, in some counties, other inferior courts, usually arranged chronologically. In most counties, records also include executions issued supplementary to criminal actions. Series 10, subseries 928, Miscellaneous Records, may also include loose criminal actions.
    Processed criminal action papers (1878-1917) are arranged in chronological order and housed in 3 archival document cases numbered CR.001.326.1-3.
    Unprocessed criminal action papers (1918-1968) are in roughly chronological order and housed in 38 record center boxes.
  - Civil Dockets, Superior Court and Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1849-1866, 1927-1940; CR.001.CV; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    Record of civil causes expected to come to trial during term. Brings forward information from Appearance Docket and also shows pleadings of defendant, prior to ruling by court, verdict, judgment, and final orders. In most counties prior to 1820, Appearance, Trial, and Reference Dockets were maintained in one civil docket at the convenience of the clerk. With the proliferation of cases after 1820, most clerks began keeping the various civil dockets in separate volumes. After 1868, this information was recorded in Civil Issues Dockets, including names of parties, history of cases carried forward from Summons Docket, and note of proceedings at trial. See also series AR, Appearance and Reference Docket.
    - Civil Issues Docket, 1927-1940; CR.001.322; 201.108.1; 2014.4.52; CR.001.322.1 - CR.001.322.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      v. 8 1927-1934; v. 9 1934-1940
    - Trial Dockets, 1849-1866; CR.001.309; 201.108.2; 2014.4.61; CR.001.309.1 - CR.001.309.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions.
      v1 1849-1858; v2 1858-1866
    - Record of Assignees, Receivers and Trustees, 1884-1933; CR.001.929; 201.111.4; CR.001.929.1; CR.001.929.2 - CR.001.929.3; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      chronological
      1 box, 1884-1933; v1 1895-1915; v2 1916-1933
  - Civil Action Papers, Superior Court and Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, 1870-1968; CR.001.325; 201.30; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
    Civil case files from magistrates courts, Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions, Superior Court, and, in some counties, other inferior courts. In most counties, also contains executions issued supplementary to civil judgments. [Civil actions concerning are filed separately. Other sub-groupings may include actions concerning county officials, the Board of County Commissioners, occupational licensing boards, canals, mines, and timber.
    See also Court Records subseries 328, Executions; series 10, Miscellaneous Records, subseries 924, Personal Accounts, for merchant account related to bankruptcy filings; and/or series 10, subseries 928, Miscellaneous Records, for loose civil case files, if available.
    - Civil Action Papers, 1870-1968; CR.001.325; 1977.08.08; 201.30.1; 2015.4.33; CR.001.325.1 - CR.001.325.2; CR.001.325._; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Processed records include 2 Fibredex boxes of files dated 1870-1939, 1957 and arranged chronologically.
      Unprocessed records include 131 cartons of files dated 1901-1968 and boxed in file number order.
    - Civil Action Papers Concerning Land, 1877-1915; CR.001.325; 1977.08.08; 201.30.2; CR.001.325.3 - CR.001.325.4; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    - Civil Action Papers, County Court, 1926-1968; CR.001.325; 201.30.3; 2017.11.62; 2018.8.3; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      File number
      Unprocessed County Court civil action papers (1926-1968) are in roughly file number order (#1-7004) and housed in 26 record center boxes.
  - Minute Dockets, Lower Courts, 1877-1968; CR.001.331; 201.34; Minutes; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
    Includes Minute Dockets from inferior courts.
    - Minute Docket, Inferior Court, 1877-1879; CR.001.331; 1996.5.9; 201.34.1; CR.001.331.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    - Minute Docket, General County Court, 1926-1968; CR.001.331; 201.34.2; 2012.7.127; CR.001.331.2 - CR.001.331.16; Alamance County (N.C.)
      Alamance County Clerk of Superior Court
      Vols. 1-15
    - Minute Docket, Municipal Recorders Court, 1962-1964; CR.001.331; 201.34.3; 2014.4.49; CR.001.331.17; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Volume titled Municipal Recorders Court Minute Book Number 2
  - Criminal Dockets, Lower Courts, 1947-1968; CR.001.332; 201.105; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Register of Deeds
    Includes criminal issues docket, judgment docket, execution docket, clerk's minute docket, costs docket and half fee docket from various inferior courts.
    - Criminal Docket, General County Court, 1947-1968; CR.001.332; 201.105.1; 2014.4.47; CR.001.332.1 - CR.001.332.5; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      General County Court Criminal Dockets: v.6 1945-1947; v.7 1947-1949; v.8 1949-1953; v.9 1953-1968; v.10 1968 (also contains minutes for vol. 16)
  - Justices of Peace and Magistrates, Lists and Records of, 1885-1897; CR.001.917; 201.113; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court; Register of Deeds
    Records concerning the appointment, election, qualification, and resignation of Justices of the Peace.
    - Record of Magistrates, Election and Oath, 1889-1895; CR.001.917; 201.113.1; 2014.4.68; CR.001.917.2; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    - Record of Magistrates, 1885-1897; CR.001.917; 201.113.2; 2014.4.67; CR.001.917.1; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
  - Inebriates, Lunacy, and Judicial Hospitalizations Records, 1900-1972; CR.001.919; 201.94; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
    Records include documentation of hearings for commitment of insane persons and inebriates, listing the name of the alleged lunatic, oaths of parties testifying to his/her lunacy, and copies of the clerk's order of commitment and the superintendent of the state hospital's order of release. These records are restricted by NCGS 122C-207. Records will be open 100 years from date of record per NCGS 132-11.
    See also Court Records subseries 922, Orders and Decrees and Special Proceedings.
    - Record of Inquisition of Lunacy, 1900-1972; CR.001.919; 201.94.1; 2012.7.128; 2012.7.129; 2012.7.130; 2012.7.131; 2012.7.132; CR.001.919.1 - CR.001.919.7; Alamance County (N.C.)
      Court records pertaining to judicial hospitalizations are closed per NCGS 122C-207. Records will be open 100 years from date of record per NCGS 132-11.
      CR.001.919.1: Record of Inquisition of Lunacy volume 1, 1900-1922
      CR.001.919.2: Lunacy Record volume 2, 1922-1934
      CR.001.919.3-5: Inquisition of Lunacy volumes 3-5, 1934-1959
      CR.001.919.6: Lunacy Docket volume 6, 1958-1964
      CR.001.919.7: Record of Judicial Hospitalization volume 7, 1964-1972
    - Inquisition of Inebriates, 1940-1963; CR.001.919; 201.94.6; 2012.7.133; CR.001.919.8; Alamance County (N.C.)
    - Lunacy Records, 1901-1968; CR.001.919; 201.94.7; 2017.3.6; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Unprocessed; chronological
  - Orders and Decrees and Special Proceedings, 1869-1968; CR.001.922; 201.109; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court; Register of Deeds
    Includes records created in hearings before the clerk. These have sometimes been distributed among other series of records based on subject: see also Court Records subseries 919, Inebriates, Lunacy, and Judicial Hospitalizations Records; series 4, Land and Property Records; series 5, Estates Records; and series 6, Marriage, Divorce, and Vital Statistics, subseries 604, Divorce Records, and subseries 901, Adoption Records, if available.
    - Minute Docket, Special Proceedings, 1891-1952; CR.001.922; 201.109.5; 2014.4.72; CR.001.922.1 - CR.001.922.9; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      v3 1891-1898; v4 1897-1908; v5 1907-1913; v6 1913-1918; v7 1918-1923; v8 1923-1935; v9 1938-1946; v10 1946-1949; v11 1949-1952
    - Summons Docket, Special Proceedings, 1877-1954; CR.001.922; 201.109.3; 2014.4.58; CR.001.922.12 - CR.001.922.15; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      v1 1877-1921; v2 1921-1939; v3 1939-1949; v4 1949-1954
    - Special Proceedings Papers, 1903-1965; CR.001.922; 201.109.7; 2017.11.60; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Unprocessed special proceedings papers (1903-1965) are in file number order (#467-4647) and housed in 36 record center boxes.
    - Special Proceedings, Current, 1955-1968; CR.001.922; 201.109.1; 2014.4.53; CR.001.922.21; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
    - Orders and Decrees Papers, 1905-1954; CR.001.922; 201.109.6; 2017.6.166; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Unprocessed
      Unprocessed orders and decrees (1905-1954) are in roughly book and file number order and housed in 1 archival document box.
    - Orders and Decrees & Petition, 1869-1964; CR.001.922; 201.109.2; 2014.4.54; 2014.4.71; CR.001.922.10; CR.001.922.11; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court
      Volume, CR.001.922.10, 1869-1930
      Volume 2, CR.001.922.11, 1932-1964
- Land and Property Records, CR.001.4; Alamance County (N.C.); Clerk of Superior Court; Clerk of Court of Pleas and Quarter Sessions; Register of Deeds
  This series contains records related to ownership, transfer, and taxing of land and property.
  - Deeds, 1793-1905; CR.001.401; 1964.03.18; 201.36.1; CR.001.401.1 - CR.001.401.2; Alamance County (N.C.); Duke University (Box Deeds)
    Alphabetical
    Duke University
    Records may include Record of Deeds (volumes), Index to Deeds (volumes), and original deeds left in the courthouse after being deposited with the clerk for probate and recording. These loose deeds can include various types such as deeds of sale, deeds of trust, mortgage deeds, and quitclaim (or release) deeds. Within these records, the seller is commonly referred to as the grantor, the buyer as grantee.
  - Land Sales for Taxes, 1929-1968; CR.001.407; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Duke University
    Records may include volumes and/or papers pertaining to the sale of land for nonpayment of taxes.
    - Summons Docket, Land Tax Sales, 1929-1964; CR.001.407; 201.106.3; 2014.4.73; CR.001.407.8 - CR.001.407.9; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Land Tax Sale Summons Docket)
      Land Tax Sale Summons Dockets: v1 1929-1934; v2 1940-1964
    - Judgment Docket Tax, 1958-1968; CR.001.407; 201.106.2; 2014.4.51; CR.001.407.1 - CR.001.407.5; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Tax Judgment Docket)
      Tax Judgment Dockets: v. 18 1958-1961; v. 22 1961-1962; v. 23 1962; v. 24 1962-1967; v. 29 1967-1968
    - Judgment Docket Land Tax Sales, 1930-1967; CR.001.407; 201.106.1; 2014.4.48; CR.001.407.6 - CR.001.407.7; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Judgment Docket Land Tax Sales)
      v.1 1930-1952, v.3 1943-1967
    - Tax Suits, 1929-1961; CR.001.407; 201.106.4; 2018.7.92; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Box Unprocessed Tax Suits)
      Organized by file number, #1-4742
  - Resale of Land and Foreclosures, 1921-1968; CR.001.409; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.
    Contains twentieth-century records of land sold under foreclosure by trustees and mortgagees. Case papers from foreclosure actions may also be filed in some counties as civil actions concerning land or as miscellaneous land records.
    - Record of Resale of Land by Trustees and Mortgages, 1921-1968; CR.001.409; 201.112.1; 2014.4.59; 2018.7.91; CR.001.409.1 - CR.001.409.7; Alamance County (N.C.). Clerk of Superior Court.; Clerk of Superior Court (Item Record of Resale of Land by Trustees and Mortgages, Box Unprocessed Record of Resale of Land by Trustees and Mortgages)